My friends and welcome to exercise number ninety two in this exercise, we are going to implement and
create the bubble sort algorithm and Jeff.
So let's create here in the source folder a new Java class I will call as bubble.
Sort it and I will click Enter.
I will create a new package here in order to define the algorithms inside it.
I will move the bubbles sort to this algorithm.
OK, so all the algorithms is here and the data structures are here that we have created in the previous
space.
By the way, you can get all the source codes from the from every exercise on the resources folder underneath
every exercise or every less so in an hour to get them there.
Of course.
OK.
This is the class.
This is the Java program for implementation of the of bubbles.
We start by creating a new method public
public
void, and that is called bubble sorting.
This method bubbles sorting.
It took into the parameters, the array that we are going to sort.
OK, it's very simple.
Now, as we see in the previous pages and the animation and animation video that we need to start detecting
and start comparing the two numbers that the a number that index, I enter a number at the index I +1
and we see if it is greater than we will swi or less, then we will swab or or the definition of anything.
This will be depending on whether we start from the left or started from the right.
OK.
In this example, we will start from the right and start comparing the two numbers and then we start
reserving that and consider the last one is as fully arranged, fully sorted.
OK.
So we will start and an equal in size, equal
at the thought length.
Let's define the length of their four and I are equal to zero I less than the size of the array minus
one.
This is the algorithm that tells us to do that.
And I thus plus.
OK.
We need to go through all the elements of the array.
Also, we need to create a new nested loop that goes through all the elements of the array until and
not all the elements, except that elements that they are on the left that we have fully sorted them
in order to.
To do that, we need to create four in J equal to zero g less than and minus one or size minus one minus
I.
So I is that elements, the number of elements at this index at element number of elements that they
are fully sorted.
They are considered, according to I, the same because every, every iteration in the outer loop,
we are going to reserve two fully sorted a number of I.
So consider the first iteration.
There have no at zero iteration.
We don't have any reserve, so are equal to zeros and the same size equal to zero.
So J will go through all the elements.
The after the first iteration, we have reserved one element.
We have kept one element as fully sorted.
So I would be one and so on.
OK.
So this is why we are being menacing and decrement this size by minus one minus.
This is the trick behind that, the bubble sort of algorithm.
OK.
Pay attention for this.
No.
If we need to check if the array at index is greater than at the Appendix J.
+1, so we need to swear at them.
OK, so the right is greater than the left that the right and the J.
Or the left is greater than the right, so we need to swear to them, swear.
We are starting from the end, from the right and we are moving, OK, swab.
That's Natalie.
If they attend the jail plus one and.
And that's the Appendix J.
OK, so ain't them equal to every at index chain
array at Index J Equal FDA at Index J Plus one array at Index J +1.
This is the algorithm of behind behind the swapping and we have seen this in previous videos like we
have swept them into a temporary variable and X consideration is X and G plus.
One knows why we store X equal to Y and Y equal to that them dump that was equal to that X.
This is the swapping algorithm, OK?
And we have swept them if J is greater than J plus one.
No, let's make.
A print at a print method that prints stirring so public void.
Print Saturday, it took Saturday, so we need to sort it first and then we pass it as.
Keys says.
For Loop Sport, if.
This is for this.
This is what of bad and I mean, only one part.
OK, so I need to print today that is best for me.
So in size, equal in length.
We have seen this in the previous figures many times, though, so I will make it fast.
I less than I
suppose.
Plus plus I would print system of the print everyday.
Appendix I NASA's Space
System, sort of
the current plan.
Everything OK, this is.
For the printing that we know, let's make the driver method to test the above code.
We start by making the
static void main method.
It starts drink args.
We start by creating a an instance of bubbles, sort of a support vehicle to new bubbles or object.
And we start by creating Int
Array
equal.
I will start making
the first.
OK, this is good.
Now, in order to sort them restart my bubbles, sort, we have two methods printer ray and Salt that
Ray I will start by bubble sorting and I reverse that Ray.
And after sorting, I will print system to print and after sorting,
we make bubbles or the print array that's print that.
OK, so this is our program that we have created.
This is the algorithm that I need to use from you to write it down and consider it as very important
to understand two tricks inside the nested loops that starts from high to size minus one and the outer
glue, and the second one is less than size minus one minus.
This is the trick.
OK.
And the second trip is swapping the swapping algorithm if a rate at index is greater than that index
+1.
OK.
This is starting from left to right.
Let's run and see.
Bubbles sort of start making it.
This is the array that we have 99.
And this is the sort that after using a bubble sort.
OK, so this is very important.
We have implemented their bubbles, sort you correctly, and the above functions always run to end to
power too, because we have nested loops.
OK?
It can be optimized by stopping the algorithm if inner loop didn't cause any swap.
So how to make an optimized version of the bubbles sort.